{"tossups": [{"question": "A monument at this site erected by the United Daughters of the Confederacy was controversial for its depiction of the \"faithful slave,\" Heyward Shepherd. Before his execution, the leader of an event at this site noted that \"the crimes of this guilty land will never be purged away, but with Blood.\" By seizing arms at this site, the leader of the Pottawatomie Massacre hoped to spark a slave revolt. For ten points, name this West Virginia town where John Brown raided a federal arsenal.", "answer": "<b><u>Harpers Ferry</u></b> Armory, West Virginia", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "While on his way to participate in this activity, Charles VIII of France died by striking his head on a lintel door. Members of the Third Estate vowed \"not to separate and to reassemble wherever necessary, until the Constitution of the kingdom is established\" in an \"Oath\" named for the location of this activity during the French Revolution. The aviator Roland Garros names a stadium in Paris dedicated to, for ten points, what sport, whose best players compete at the French Open and Wimbledon?", "answer": "<b><u>Tennis</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "The first woman to win this award earned a PhD in political science from UCLA but won this award by demonstrating successful management of common property. That woman, Elinor Ostrom, was later joined by the only other woman to win this prize, Esther Dufflo, who, along with her husband, won in 2019 for their experimental approach to alleviating global poverty. Ragnar Frisch and Jan Tinbergen were the first recipients of, for ten points, what prestigious global award in the field of social science?", "answer": "<b><u>Nobel</u></b> Memorial Prize in <b><u>Economic</u></b> Sciences (or Sveriges Riksbank Prize in <b><u>Economic</u></b> Sciences in Memory of Alfred <b><u>Nobel</u></b>, accept <b><u>Economics</u></b> in place of <b><u>Economic</u> </b>Sciences)", "metadata": "Social Science - Social Science - Economics"}, {"question": "During this war, over 350 tribal forces were killed when Lord Chelmsford led his forces into Natal Province at the Battle of Rorke\u2019s Drift. This war began when King Cetshwayo rejected an ultimatum from the High Commissioner, Sir Henry Bartle Frere, in 1879. This war is known for several particularly bloody battles, including a decisive British loss against a technologically inferior foe at the Battle of Isandlwana. For ten points, name this war that took place in modern-day South Africa.", "answer": "Anglo-<b><u>Zulu</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "One of the first modern arguments for this theory was advanced during the English Civil War by Thomas Hobbes in <em>Leviathan</em>. According to one work titled for this concept, man is \"born free and everywhere he is in chains.\" Espoused by Enlightenment thinkers such as Jean-Jacques Rousseau and John Locke, this concept is implicit in the United States Constitution. For ten points, what is this political theory suggesting that rulers derive their authority from the consent of the people?", "answer": "<b><u>Social contract</u></b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "In this state, Clark Kerr declined to expel student protestors belonging to the Mario Savio-led Free Speech movement. Allan Bakke [[BAHK-ee]] was denied entry to medical school in this state under an affirmative action policy upheld in a 1978 Supreme Court decision. In 2020, a judge ruled that this state\u2019s university system can no longer use ACT and SAT scores as a factor in admissions. For ten points, what state\u2019s public university system includes campuses at Irvine and Berkeley?", "answer": "<b><u>California</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The pro-democratic Cylon and Ninon helped expel this man from Crotone [[croh-TOH-nay]] after he helped defeat Sybaris. This man studied the relationship between string length and musical note pitch, devising the Harmony of the Spheres theory for the planets. This man banned eating fava beans, and one of his followers was killed for revealing the existence of irrational numbers. For ten points, name this Greek polymath whose namesake theory says a squared plus b squared equals c squared.", "answer": "<b><u>Pythagoras</u></b> of Samos (prompt on \"Pythagorean\")", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {"question": "Inflation increased during this man\u2019s reign due to his heavy borrowing from the Fugger family. This led to this man sponsoring an expedition to find the legendary city of El Dorado in modern Venezuela. This monarch passed the Edict of Worms, calling for the capture of Martin Luther. Francisco Pizarro and Hernan Cort\u00e9s conquered the Incan and Aztec Empires respectively during this man\u2019s reign. For ten points, name this Habsburg Holy Roman Emperor who ruled both Austria and Spain.", "answer": "<b><u>Charles V</u></b> (accept <b><u>Carlos I</u></b> or <b><u>Charles I</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In 1838, W.W. Phelps and John Whitmer established Far West, Missouri based on this man\u2019s design plan. This man died in 1844, when a mob stormed the Carthage, Illinois jail in which he was being held. This man claimed to have experienced a vision in 1823 in which an angel directed him to a buried book of golden plates, which he would later transcribe into his new church\u2019s foundational book. For ten points, name this man, the founder of Mormonism and the Latter Day Saints movement.", "answer": "Joseph <b><u>Smith</u></b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "The man who led these events faced a personal excommunication from Pope Alexander VI and ultimately execution after a thorough investigation from Sebastian Maggi [[MAH-jee]]. The \u201cWeepers\u201d were supporters of these mass gatherings, and the artist Sandro Botticelli supposedly contributed many of his own works, particularly those including nudity, to these events. For ten points, name these events that culminated on February 7, 1497 when followers of Savonarola burned thousands of \u201csinful\u201d objects.", "answer": "<b><u>Bonfire of the Vanities</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "This person nominated Harriet Miers to the Supreme Court, and under his administration, Scooter Libby was implicated in the Valerie Plame Affair. This president devised the No Child Left Behind Act. This man also landed on the USS <em>Abraham Lincoln</em> and gave the \u201cMission Accomplished\u201d speech, despite the fact that the Iraq War was still being fought. This man declared, \"I can hear you\" when speaking to first responders while standing next to a fireman with a bull horn. For ten points, name this US president from Texas who faced 9/11.", "answer": "George <b><u>W</u></b>alker <b><u>Bush</u></b> (accept <b><u>Bush 43</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this war, the <em>Glorioso</em> survived attacks at the Azores and Cape Finisterre with millions of silver dollars on board. Sardinian forces defended Villafranca in this war, and George Townshend also blockaded Genoa. Fog and snow, as well as inexperience, did not stop Frederick the Great from winning at Mollwitz during this war. After this war ended with the Treaty of Aix-la-Chapelle, Prussia allied with Britain in the Diplomatic Revolution. For ten points, name this war that challenged Maria Theresa's right to inherit the Hapsburg Empire.", "answer": "War of the <b><u>Austrian Succession</u></b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Peter Lawford and this man organized the Inaugural Gala for JFK, but he later changed parties and arranged the gala for Ronald Reagan in 1980. This man built the Cal Neva Lodge & Casino at Lake Tahoe and opened its Celebrity Room. Mikhail Gorbachev and Gennadi Gerasimov sarcastically named a doctrine for this man in which Warsaw Pact states gained independence. Genovese crime boss Willie Moretti was the godfather of, for ten points, what Italian-American singer, known as \u201cOl\u2019 Blue Eyes\u201d?", "answer": "Frank <b><u>Sinatra</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "After bombs planted by a terrorist cell ignited in this province\u2019s CN Railway, John Diefenbaker asked \u201cIs this Ireland?\u201d while on national television. This province successfully transitioned from Roman Catholic run health institutions to public healthcare during its \u201cQuiet Revolution.\u201d Only used during the World Wars, one Prime Minister revived the War Measures Act in this Canadian province during the 1970s October Crisis. For ten points, name this Francophone Canadian province with the city of Montreal.", "answer": "<b><u>Quebec</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "To build the hydrogen bomb, this company built and operated the Savannah River Site. This company created a brochure called \"Farming with Dynamite\" which promoted using explosives to remove obstacles. This company began by making gunpowder at the Eleutherian Mills for the US Army. This company created the ozone layer-damaging chlorofluorocarbon Freon. Some of this company's products include a material for nonstick pans, Teflon, as well as the polymer Nylon. For ten points, name this Delaware-based chemical company.", "answer": "E.I. <b><u>DuPont</u></b> de Nemours and Company (accept <b><u>DuPont</u></b> de Nemours, Inc.)  In 2017, the original duPont company merged with this other chemical company that was boycotted during the Vietnam War for its production of napalm.  ANSWER: The <b><u>Dow</u></b> Chemical Company (prompt on \"TDCC\")", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "A college without walls was named for this man in Mount Angel. Ferdinand Marcos gave this man an honorary doctorate at the Eastern University following a trip in which this man praised Marcos\u2019s martial law. A group organized by this man was situated at The Forty Acres, and this man negotiated with Lionel Steinberg in the Coachella area of California. This man organized the Delano Grape Strike, and with Dolores Huerta, this man co-founded the National Farm Workers Association. For ten points, name this Mexican-American labor leader.", "answer": "C\u00e9sar <b><u>Ch\u00e1vez</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This man was the second president of the Royal Academy, and his <em>The Graces</em> <em>Unveiling Nature</em> is displayed at the center of the Academy today. This artist depicted a man in a green top kneeling next to a man holding a ream of cloth in a painting set at Shackamaxon. This painter of <em>Penn\u2019s Treaty with the Indians</em> depicted a muscular Native American resting his chin on his fist on the left side of a work set on a battlefield outside of Quebec City. For ten points, what American artist painted <em>The Death of General Wolfe</em>?", "answer": "Benjamin <b><u>West</u> </b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "The Old Vineyards were attacked at this battle, and during this battle, the sun overcame the fog, allowing St. Hilaire's men to attack the heights. A general at this battle said, \u201cOne sharp blow and the war is over.\u201d Artillery broke the ice at this battle, causing men to drown in the Satschan ponds. This battle featured an attack on the Pratzen Heights and led to the creation of the Confederation of the Rhine and the signing of the Treaty of Pressburg. Russians and Austrians lost to Napoleon in, for ten points, what 1805 battle?", "answer": "Battle of <b><u>Austerlitz</u></b> (accept Battle of the <b><u>Three Emperors</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "Society George Bird Grinnel founded named for a French-American bird watcher.", "answer": "National <b><u>Audubon</u></b> Society", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Structures some Conservationists oppose, such as the Glen Canyon version on the Colorado River.", "answer": "<b><u>Dam</u> </b>  April 22 celebration of the protection our planet, proposed by Gaylord Nelson. (3)  ANSWER: <b><u>Earth Day</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Scottish-American who preserved Yosemite and founded the Sierra Club.", "answer": "John <b><u>Muir</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Minnesota presidential candidate who the Sierra Club supported against Ronald Reagan in 1984.", "answer": "Walter \"Fritz\" <b><u>Mondale</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Reservoir in Yosemite over which Conservationists and Preservationists fought about the water supply.", "answer": "<b><u>Hetch Hetchy</u> </b>", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "Supreme Court Justice who suggested that environmental objects like valleys can be granted personhood in the <em>Morton</em> case.", "answer": "William O. <b><u>Douglas</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "Ivy League school which operates the eBird program at its Lab of Ornithology in Sapsucker Woods.", "answer": "<b><u>Cornell</u></b> University", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {"question": "Season which names a war between Finland and the USSR, stalemated in part due to cold weather.", "answer": "<b><u>Winter</u></b> War", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {"question": "Finnish capital which hosted the 1952 Winter Olympics.", "answer": "<b><u>Helsinki</u> </b>  Russian tsar who lost control of Finland after the Bolshevik Revolution destabilized (3)  his regime.  ANSWER: <b><u>Nicholas II</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Nearby Baltic nation that was invaded by Finnish forces in the Kinship Wars.", "answer": "<b><u>Estonia</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Historical region of southeastern Finland that it was forced to cede to the USSR in 1940.", "answer": "<b><u>Karelia</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Red Army nickname for Finnish soldier Simo H\u00e4yh\u00e4 [[HIGH-hah]] for his success as a sniper.", "answer": "The <b><u>White Death</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "War fought by the Finns and Nazis in an effort to regain Finnish territory from the Soviets during World War Two.", "answer": "<b><u>Continuation</u></b> War", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "President of Finland during the Interim Peace, who was sentenced to ten years in prison for his involvement with the Axis.", "answer": "Risto <b><u>Ryti</u></b> [[REE-stoh RYOO-tee]]", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "Holy Middle Eastern city where the predecessor of Hamas set up branches.", "answer": "<b><u>Jerusalem</u> </b>", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Islamic sect Hamas supports, as contrasted with Shia Islam.", "answer": "<b><u>Sunni</u></b> Islam", "metadata": "Religion - Religion"}, {"question": "Strip of land bordering Egypt and Israel which Hamas governs.", "answer": "<b><u>Gaza</u></b> Strip", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Weapons Hamas uses, defended from by Israel\u2019s Iron Dome.", "answer": "<b><u>Rockets</u></b> (accept \"artillery shells,\" \"missiles,\" and other similar descriptive answers)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Egyptian organization from which Hamas stems, upon which Nasser cracked down.", "answer": "<b><u>Muslim Brotherhood</u></b> (or Society of the <b><u>Muslim Brothers</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Hamas was formed after the first of these Palestinian uprisings against Israel that often involved civilians throwing projectiles.", "answer": "<b><u>Intifada</u> </b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "Military wing of Hamas, as contrasted with the Dawah.", "answer": "Izz ad-Din <b><u>al-Qassam</u></b> Brigades (accept <b><u>EQB</u></b>)   1994 Massacre of Muslims by Baruch Goldstein, which prompted Hamas to start (8)  targeting civilians.  ANSWER: <b><u>Cave of the Patriarchs</u></b> Massacre (or <b><u>Ibrahimi Mosque</u></b> Massacre; or <b><u>Hebron</u> </b>Massacre)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Corruption in this federal agency, abetted by the first female administrator of</u></b> <b><u>this agency, Anne Gorsuch, was uncovered in the early-1980\u2019s. Members of this</u></b> <b><u>agency were taken hostage by protestors led by Lois Gibbs during the Love (+)</u> Canal Crisis. This agency was originally formed in response to fiascos like the waste-fueled fires on the Cuyahoga River. The publication of Rachel Carson\u2019s (*) </b><em>Silent Spring</em> was key to the movement that led to the Nixon administration\u2019s creation of, for ten points, what federal agency intended to fight pollution?", "answer": "<b><u>Environmental Protection</u></b> Agency (or <b><u>EPA</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "<b><u>This union published the Hungarian newsletter</u> </b><em><b><u>B\u00e9rmunk\u00e1s</u></b></em><b><u>. Members of this</u></b> <b><u>union were charged with treason as the Sydney Twelve after the Tottenham Tragedy.</u></b> <b><u>\"Slim\" Evans, part of the On-To-Ottawa trek, was once a member of this group, which</u></b> <b><u>was housed in the Finnish (*)</u> Labor Temple in Canada. This union made the </b><em><b>Little Red </b><b>Songbook</b></em><b> and wrote songs like \"There'll Be Pie in the Sky.\u201d Mother Jones and (*) </b>Big Bill Haywood were among the founders of this group, which advocated \"one great union.\" For ten points, name this labor union of \"Wobblies.\u201d", "answer": "<b><u>Industrial Workers of the World</u></b> (accept <b><u>IWW</u></b>; accept <b><u>Wobblies</u></b> before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Born with the surname Gelbfisz, this man formed a partnership with Cecil B.</u></b> <b><u>DeMille in 1913 to produce feature-length motion pictures. This man battled Adolph</u></b> <b><u>Zukor for control over Paramount Pictures and lost, after which this man created his</u></b> <b><u>own film studio under a (+)</u> new surname. In 1946, the Academy of Motion Picture Arts and Sciences awarded this man the Thalberg Memorial Award for his contributions to the medium of (*) </b>film. For ten points, name this mogul from the Golden Age of Hollywood whose name contributes a letter to the film studio MGM.", "answer": "Samuel <b><u>Goldwyn</u></b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {"question": "<b><u>In the 1960s, this site was excavated by Yigael Yadin, who discovered 28</u></b> <b><u>human remains and a number of bathhouses. Lucius Flavius Silva laid siege to this</u></b> <b><u>site and constructed a massive siege ramp completed in 73 CE. (+)</u> Josephus wrote of two speeches that a Sicari leader made at this site convincing his men to kill themselves. Herod the Great built two palaces for himself at this site, which was besieged following the First (*) </b>Jewish War. For ten points, name this fortress captured by the Roman army in the Judaean Desert, which overlooks the Dead Sea.", "answer": "<b><u>Masada</u></b>", "metadata": "History - Ancient History"}, {"question": "<b><u>In 1948, one of this sea\u2019s many islands, which is now part of the mainland,</u></b> <b><u>became the site of a secret bioweapons facility. In the early 1960s, the Amu Darya and</u></b> <b><u>Syr Darya rivers were diverted from this sea to provide desert (+)</u> irrigation in support of the burgeoning Uzbek cotton farming industry. The Dike Kokoral dam was completed in 2005 in an attempt to replenish this sea\u2019s (*) </b>diminishing water level. For ten points, name this sea, whose drainage basin encompasses nearly 600,000 square miles in Central Asia.", "answer": "<b><u>Aral</u></b> Sea", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "<b><u>Shaul Ladany warned people of this event of which \"Issa\" and \"Tony\" were the</u></b> <b><u>leaders. The codeword \u201cSunshine\u201d was supposed to be used during an attack in this</u></b> <b><u>event. Andre Spitzer was clubbed in view of cameras during this event. Because of</u></b> <b><u>this event, (+)</u> GSG 9 was created and Ahmed Bouchiki was accidentally killed in Lillehammer, Norway. Israel launched Operation (*) </b>Wrath of God to target perpetrators of this event which Abu Daoud might have planned for Black September.  Occurring at the 1972 Olympics, for ten points, name this massacre of Jewish athletes.", "answer": "<b><u>Munich</u></b> Massacre (accept <b><u>Black September</u></b> Massacre before mentioned; accept <b><u>1972 Olympic</u></b>s Massacre before mentioned; accept \"Kidnapping,\" \"Killing,\" and other words that indicate knowledge of the violence perpetrated in place of <b><u>Massacre</u></b>)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "<b><u>Donald Trump circumvented this act by using \"Schedule F appointments\"</u></b> <b><u>when he signed an October 2020 Executive Order, an act being described by political</u></b> <b><u>scientists as \u201copen cronyism.\u201d The Franklin Pierce administration developed a</u></b> <b><u>predecessor to this act by creating a (+)</u> civil service exam for Cabinet staff. Deranged office seeker Charles J. Guiteau's assassination of President James Garfield led to (*) </b>reformers pushing this act through in 1883. For ten points, name this civil service reform that attempted to weaken the spoils system in American politics.", "answer": "<b><u>Pendleton</u></b> Civil Service Reform Act", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This woman earned a PhD from Columbia\u2019s Department of Public Law and</u></b> <b><u>Governance and became a professor at Georgetown in 1982. When introducing</u></b> <b><u>Hillary Clinton in 2016, this woman said, \u201cThere is a special place in hell for (+)</u></b> <b>women who don\u2019t help each other.\u201d In 2012, this woman had a tense meeting with a group of activists from her homeland as a result of her role in the NATO bombing of Serbia. This native of (*) </b>Czechoslovakia was nominated to her highest post by President Bill Clinton. For ten points, name this woman, the first female Secretary of State.", "answer": "Madeleine <b><u>Albright</u></b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "<b><u>This country entered \"Rubik Agreements\" over its anonymity laws.</u></b> <b><u>Christopher Meili and Bradley Birkenfeld broke this country's secrecy laws as</u></b> <b><u>whistleblowers. British politicians criticized this country's \"gnome\" (+)</u> bankers. Assets are protected by this country's 1934 Federal Act on Banks and Savings Banks. A company in this country uses the 3 keys logo. (*) </b>Lugano is one of this country's banking hubs, and it is where UBS is located. For ten points, name this country with cities including Basel and Lausanne.", "answer": "<b><u>Switzerland</u></b> (or <b><u>Swiss Confederation</u></b>)", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {}], "bonuses": []}